Guide to the Doris Duke Photograph Collection, 1870-2006
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Doris Duke Photograph collection 1880-2006
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke, Doris, 1912-1993
56.6 linear feet Extent: approximately 12,000 Items
Doris Duke was the only child of James Buchanan (J.B.) Duke, a founder of the American Tobacco Company and Duke Energy Company and a benefactor of Duke University, and Nanaline Holt Duke. Inheriting a bulk of her father's estate in 1925, which included Duke Farms in New Jersey, Rough Point in Newport, R.I., and a mansion in New York City, Doris was soon dubbed by the press as "the richest girl in the world." Although Doris did her best to live a private life, she carried on the Duke family's pattern of philanthropy by contributing to a number of public causes such as the arts, historic preservation, and the environment. Doris Duke died in October 1993 at the age of 80. In her will she left the majority of her estate to the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation. The Doris Duke Photograph Collection was created by combining color and black and white photographs, slides, negatives, and other photographic formats contained in albums, boxes, picture frames, and envelopes.
RL.00319
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Doris Duke Photograph Collection was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a donation from the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation in June 2009.
Collection Overview
The Doris Duke Photograph Collection was created by combining color and black and white photographs, slides, negatives, and other photographic formats contained in albums, boxes, picture frames, and envelopes into groupings closely mirroring the collections that constitute the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation Historical Archives. The collection covers the years 1870 to 2006 and is organized into twelve series: Doris Duke, Duke Endowment, Duke Farms, Duke Gardens, Duke Family, Falcon Lair, General, New York Apartments/New York Mansion, Newport Restoration Foundation, Rough Point, Southeast Asian Art and Culture (SEAAC), and Shangri La.
In cases where the copyright of the image does not belong to the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation, these are noted in the finding aid and use restrictions/citation information is included when possible.
Subject Headings
Cromwell, James H. R. (James Henry Roberts), b. 1896; Duke family; Duke, Doris, 1912-1993; Duke, James Buchanan, 1856-1925; Duke, Nanaline Holt Inman; International travel
Related Material
Duke Family Papers, 1885-1992 (bulk 1892-1927)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Doris Duke Papers, 1798-2003 and undated (bulk 1930-1999)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Doris Duke Papers on the Duke Farms Residence, 1859-2004 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Doris Duke Papers on the Rough Point Residence, 1922-1997
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Doris Duke Papers on the Shangri La Residence, 1932-2003
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Newport Restoration Foundation Records, 1968-1999
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Contents of Collection
- Doris Duke, 1913-1998
  This series documents Doris Duke's life from the time she was an infant to a few years before and after her death in 1993. The photographs, slides, and negatives are grouped by topic and therefore do not always share the same creation date nor are they necessarily the same formats. Topics include social events, passport photos, life at her various residences, travel, her time as a war correspondent, her honeymoon, her many animals at the various residences, and her jewelry and dresses. Of particular interest are the color glass mounted slides of Doris Duke's trip to the Middle East in 1938.
  RESTRICTED: Access to photographs in group PHDD050 are temporarily restricted and require prior written approval from the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation to view.
  - Portraits of Doris Duke, dressed in tweed coat and hat, standing in front of small clipper plane. Logo on side of plan reads, "Boston Maine Central Vermont No. 21...", circa 1945 (Box 1, Folder PHDD001)
  - Portrait of Doris Duke, as a young girl, reading. Portrait is a profile shot, circa 1925 (Box 1, Folder PHDD003)
  - Portraits of Doris Duke at a photo shoot at Falcon Lair, circa 1965 (Box 1, Folder PHDD004)
  - Series of passport photos of Doris Duke, 1930-1990 (Box 1, Folder PHDD005)
  - Black and white photographs of Doris Duke. All are headshots, not posed, 1940-1945 (Box 1, Folder PHDD006)
  - Copy of black and white photo of Doris Duke setting cornerstone at Duke University, 1928 Jun 5. Original is in Duke University Archives Photograph Collection, 1928 (Box 1, Folder PHDD007)
  - Photos of Doris Duke with small dog. Photo most likely taken at Duke Farms, 1930-1940 (Box 1, Folder PHDD008)
  - Photo of Doris Duke dressed in horseriding garb. Photo most likely taken at Duke Farms, 1920-1930 (Box 1, Folder PHDD009)
  - Portrait of Doris Duke, as a young girl, playing with dog in grass, circa 1915 (Box 1, Folder PHDD010)
  - Photos of Doris Duke, wearing sailor suit outfit. Location is unidentified, possibly Stotesbury home, Whitemarsh Hall, located in Wyndmoor, PA. Older gentleman in photo is Edward Stotesbury. Young woman with dark hair is possibly one of Mr. Stotesbury's daughters from his first marriage, circa 1934 (Box 1, Folder PHDD011)
  - Black and white portrait of Doris Duke as a young child, 1913-1914 (Box 1, Folder PHDD019)
  - Portrait of Doris Duke as an infant in her carriage. Photographer E.A. Jacobs, 1913 May (Box 1, Folder PHDD020)
  - Contact sheet containing twelve images of Doris Duke wearing elegant dress with matching headpiece. Photos taken on her wedding day to Porfirio Rubirosa, 1947 Sep 1 (Box 1, Folder PHDD022)
  - Black and white photographs of Doris Duke dressed in shorts, possibly at Duke Farms, 1920-1930 (Box 1, Folder PHDD023)
  - Black and white photograph of Doris Duke, dressed in long dress, gloves, and hat. Photo taken in profile, 1930-1940 (Box 1, Folder PHDD024)
  - Black and white photograph of Doris Duke dressed in evening attire. Photo appeared in Town & Country magazine. Includes 6 color slides that have not been digitized, 1983 (Box 1, Folder PHDD025)
  - Black and white photographs of Doris Duke dressed in evening attire and smiling. Photo was taken from the shoulders up. Original located in Duke University Archives, 1949 (Box 1, Folder PHDD026)
  - Color photos of Doris Duke wearing a mustard color suit. Her hair is pulled back. Location is unknown, circa 1948 (Box 1, Folder PHDD027)
  - Color photos of Doris Duke disguised in a blond, curly wig. Doris Duke often wore a wig when she sang in the First Baptist Church of Nutley's choir, circa 1971 (Box 1, Folder PHDD028)
  - Black and white photograph of caricature-like artwork of Doris Duke. Piece shows Doris Duke, with arms crossed, sitting on a sofa. A dog appears in the background, undated (Box 1, Folder PHDD029)
  - Black and white portrait of Doris Duke as a young girl. In this portrait, Doris wears a string of pearls and a lace top, circa 1918 (Box 1, Folder PHDD030)
  - Color photos of litter of puppies belonging to Doris Duke. Folder also includes two shots of a baby deer, circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder PHDD031)
  - Series of photos removed from a blue photo album. Documents Doris's European travel trip of 1923 with friends and family. Group traveled aboard on the S.S. Majestic. One place they visited was Stonehenge, England, 1923-1924 (1 of 2) (Box 1, Folder PHDD032)
  - Series of photos, also removed from a blue album, that show Doris, as a young girl, in Newport, in Hillsborough, and with friends. File also contains photos of young Doris ice skating and playing tennis 1923-1924 (2 of 2) (Box 1, Folder PHDD032)
  - Black and white photographs of Doris Duke, 1930-1935 (Box 2, Folder PHDD002)
  - Black and white portraits of Doris Duke wearing white dress and pearls. Some photos portray Miss Duke with her veil, 1935 (Box 3, Folder PHDD012)
  - Black and white portrait of Doris Duke, wearing pearls and a v neck top, 1930-1935 (Box 3, Folder PHDD013)
  - Black and white portraits of Doris Duke taken as proofs. Miss Duke is wearing lace and pearls, undated (Box 3, Folder PHDD014)
  - Black and white portraits of Doris Duke, dressed in a plaid top and pearls,1960-1965 (Box 3, Folder PHDD015)
  - Black and white portraits of Doris Duke, 1939-1940 (Box 3, Folder PHDD016)
  - Black and white portraits of Doris Duke dressed in several different outfits with teased hair and long eye lashes, circa 1970 (1 of 2) (Box 3, Folder PHDD018)
  - Black and white portraits of Doris Duke dressed in several different outfits with teased hair and long eye lashes, circa 1970 (2 of 2) (Box 3, Folder PHDD018)
  - Black and white photographs relating to Doris Duke's journey on the Aquitania to New York with friends, 1926 (Box 3, Folder PHDD052)
  - Black and white portraits of Doris Duke, circa 1930 (1 of 4) (Box 4, Folder PHDD017)
  - Black and white portraits of Doris Duke, circa 1930 (2 of 4) (Box 4, Folder PHDD017)
  - Black and white portraits of Doris Duke, circa 1930 (3 of 4) (Box 4, Folder PHDD017)
  - Black and white portraits of Doris Duke, circa 1930 (4 of 4) (Box 4, Folder PHDD017)
  - Photo layout page for Hearst Predate with various photos of Doris Duke from her early years to present, 1949 (Box 4, Folder PHDD093)
  - Portraits of Doris Duke, in color and Black and white, in various poses. Includes one image that has not been digitized, 1953 (1 of 3) (Box 5, Folder PHDD021)
  - Portraits of Doris Duke, in color and Black and white, in various poses. Includes one image that has not been digitized, 1953 (2 of 3) (Box 5, Folder PHDD021)
  - Portraits of Doris Duke, in color and Black and white, in various poses. Includes one image that has not been digitized, 1953 (3 of 3) (Box 5, Folder PHDD021)
  - Series of Black and white photographs documenting Doris Duke's early days. Photos were mainly taken at Duke Farms. Other photos include portraits of Angier and Tony Duke, sons of Angier Duke and Cordelia Biddle Duke, and other children, 1915-1920 (Box 6, Folder PHDD033)
  - Doris Duke's class portrait, probably from kindergarten. Doris is seated in the front row and center. She has her hands folded in her lap, 1915-1920 (Box 6, Folder PHDD034)
  - Color photos of Doris Duke with flower in hair. Location is possibly Italy or Spain, circa 1960 (Box 6, Folder PHDD035)
  - Selection of Black and white photographs documenting Doris Duke's volunteer work for the United States Government during World War II in Italy, 1943-1946 (Box 6, Folder PHDD036)
  - Black and white photographs of Doris Duke Cromwell with USS Port and Gulf Chairman and Port Area Committee members in New Orleans, Louisiana. File also includes shots aboard the SS McCloskey, 1944 Jun (Box 6, Folder PHDD037)
  - Black and white photographs of Doris Duke meeting and working with members of the U.S. Seamen's Service in New Orleans, Louisiana, 1944 (Box 6, Folder PHDD038)
  - Black and white photographs of Doris Duke and guests on board the SS James B. Duke celebrating its launch. Christening of ship took place on the docks of the J.A. Jones Construction Company, Georgia, 1944 (Box 6, Folder PHDD039)
  - Black and white photograph of Doris Duke talking with another guest at a black tie affair, undated (Box 6, Folder PHDD040)
  - Black and white photograph of (L to R) Col. Tex McCrary, Doris Duke, and [General George S. Patton] eating and talking at a dinner party, air force base. Handwritten notes around border of photo is possibly dialogue from the night, circa 1970 (Box 6, Folder PHDD041)
  - Black and white photographs of Doris Duke's cats and kittens resting and eating. Location is Shangri La. Images shown with this record are only a sampling from record. Other images are similar, circa 1950s (Box 6, Folder PHDD042)
  - Black and white photographs of Doris Duke's husky on leash and in yard, undated (Box 6, Folder PHDD043)
  - Black and white photographs of Doris Duke's dog, resting on beach, with unidentified woman, circa 1950 (Box 6, Folder PHDD044)
  - Black and white photographs of Doris Duke's mother German Shepherd and new litter of puppies, undated (Box 6, Folder PHDD045)
  - Black and white photographs of some of Doris Duke's dogs and puppies, circa 1950 (Box 6, Folder PHDD046)
  - Black and white photographs of Doris Duke's dogs in the back of her residence at Duke Farms, 1949-1950 (Box 6, Folder PHDD047)
  - Color photos of Doris Duke's dogs at Falcon Lair, CA. German Shepherds were Ricky and Michele, 1958 Jun 2 (Box 6, Folder PHDD048)
  - Doris Duke, dressed in corduroy suit, socializing with two men and two women, circa 1950 (Box 6, Folder PHDD049)
  - Series of color photographs removed from acidic album. Casual shots of Doris Duke, Joey Castro, and their travels. Locations include Duke Farms, Shangri La, Rough Point, Tahiti, and Spain, 1960-1965 (1 of 7) (Box 6, Folder PHDD050)
  - Series of color photographs removed from acidic album. Casual shots of Doris Duke, Joey Castro, and their travels. Locations include Duke Farms, Shangri La, Rough Point, Tahiti, and Spain, 1960-1965 (2 of 7) (Box 6, Folder PHDD050)
  - Series of color photographs removed from acidic album. Casual shots of Doris Duke, Joey Castro, and their travels. Locations include Duke Farms, Shangri La, Rough Point, Tahiti, and Spain, 1960-1965 (3 of 7) (Box 7, Folder PHDD050)
  - Series of color photographs removed from acidic album. Casual shots of Doris Duke, Joey Castro, and their travels. Locations include Duke Farms, Shangri La, Rough Point, Tahiti, and Spain, 1960-1965 (4 of 7) (Box 7, Folder PHDD050)
  - Series of color photographs removed from acidic album. Casual shots of Doris Duke, Joey Castro, and their travels. Locations include Duke Farms, Shangri La, Rough Point, Tahiti, and Spain, 1960-1965 (5 of 7) (Box 7, Folder PHDD050)
  - Series of color photographs removed from acidic album. Casual shots of Doris Duke, Joey Castro, and their travels. Locations include Duke Farms, Shangri La, Rough Point, Tahiti, and Spain, 1960-1965 (6 of 7) (Box 7, Folder PHDD050)
  - Series of color photographs removed from acidic album. Casual shots of Doris Duke, Joey Castro, and their travels. Locations include Duke Farms, Shangri La, Rough Point, Tahiti, and Spain, 1960-1965 (7 of 7) (Box 7, Folder PHDD050)
  - Color photos of Doris Duke on trips to Lamu, Nairobi and Rome. Photos compiled in light blue scrapbook by the man or host in Lamu (Charles Asfar?) Photos removed from scrapbook and handwritten notes photocopied, 1970-1975 (Box 7, Folder PHDD051)
  - Black and white photograph of a photograph of Doris Duke, undated (Box 7, Folder PHDD053)
  - Black and white photographs of Doris Duke swimming with James Cromwell, most likely in a lake at Duke Farms. File also includes a photo of three dogs and swans, 1935-1939 (Box 7, Folder PHDD054)
  - Black and white photographs of Doris Duke's jewelry. First image is of #25, Cartier necklace, second image is #3, Indian necklace, 2003 (Box 8, Folder PHDD055)
  - Black and white photographs that document Doris Duke's meeting with Eleanor Roosevelt. Images include Doris Duke, James Cromwell, and Marian Paschal, 1935-1940 (Box 8, Folder PHDD056)
  - Color photos of "Joy," Doris Duke's Shitzu at Shangri La, 1994-1998 (Box 8, Folder PHDD057)
  - Slides of Doris Duke's jewelry taken soon after jewelry was taken to Christie's for trustees to examine, 1996-1997 (Box 8, Folder PHDD058)
  - Black and white photographs of Doris Duke, Marian Paschal, James Cromwell, and Mary Crane. Photos are duplicates of originals belonging to William Hope, son of Mary Crane, 1935-1940 (Box 8, Folder PHDD059)
  - Black and white photographs of Doris Duke, in bathing suit, standing with unidentified older man and young girl at a beach boardwalk, 1944 (Box 8, Folder PHDD060)
  - Black and white photographs of Doris Duke with actors of Universal Pictures Co., Inc. Doris Duke is wearing a polka dot headscarf and chess piece pin, 1940 (Box 8, Folder PHDD061)
  - Black and white photographs of Doris Duke signing a paper before a man in a pin-striped suit on the other side of the desk, 1937 (Box 8, Folder PHDD062)
  - Black and white photographs of Doris Duke, James Cromwell, and friends, on vacation, possibly somewhere in Europe and Hawaii. Includes negatives, 1935-1940 (Box 8, Folder PHDD063)
  - Black and white photographs of Doris Duke, on skis, with an unidentified man, 1930-1935 (Box 8, Folder PHDD064)
  - Color photos documenting Doris Duke's trip to the Philippines, 1979 Feb (Box 8, Folder PHDD065)
  - Selection of Black and white photographs of Doris Duke's honeymoon to Egypt, India, Indonesia, Thailand, China, and Japan. Includes a group photo with Gandhi, 1935 (1 of 2) (Box 8, Folder PHDD067)
  - Selection of Black and white photographs of Doris Duke's honeymoon to Egypt, India, Indonesia, Thailand, China, and Japan. Includes a group photo with Gandhi, 1935 (2 of 2) (Box 8, Folder PHDD067)
  - Color photo of Doris Duke with unidentified man, possibly Charles Asfar of Asfar & Sarkis, Lebanon, 1950-1955 (Box 8, Folder PHDD068)
  - Photo of signage at Malabar Farm. Sign reads "Doris Duke Woods", 1982 (Box 8, Folder PHDD069)
  - Photos of Doris Duke, playing with dogs, on front lawn of main residence, undated (Box 8, Folder PHDD070)
  - Photos of Doris Duke's pets mainly at Falcon Lair. Included in folder is 1 photo of a dog at Duke Farms, circa 1958 (Box 8, Folder PHDD071)
  - Selection of Black and white photographs documenting Doris Duke's service for the US Government during WWII, 1944-1945 (Box 8, Folder PHDD072)
  - 35 mm prints of shots taken abroad during Doris Duke's war service for the US Government (WWII), 1944 (Box 8, Folder PHDD073)
  - Black and white photographs, presumably taken by Doris Duke, of troops overseas during WWII, 1944-1945 (Box 8, Folder PHDD074)
  - Selection of Black and white photographs of a ski trip. Photos include shots of group and Doris Duke. Includes some negatives, 1940 (Box 8, Folder PHDD075)
  - Black and white photographs of Doris Duke and friends feeding penguins. Also, includes photos of unidentified home, possibly Greenfield Plantation, S.C., Walker P. Inman Sr.'s home, circa 1940 (Box 8, Folder PHDD076)
  - Selection of Black and white photographs of Doris Duke's animals and/or animals at Duke Farms, circa 1950s (Box 8, Folder PHDD077)
  - Black and white photographs and negatives documenting Doris Duke's trip to the Middle East. Negatives, 1938 (1 of 13) (Box 9, Folder PHDD066)
  - Black and white photographs and negatives documenting Doris Duke's trip to the Middle East. Negatives, 1938 (2 of 13) (Box 9, Folder PHDD066)
  - Black and white photographs and negatives documenting Doris Duke's trip to the Middle East. Negatives, 1938 (3 of 13) (Box 9, Folder PHDD066)
  - Black and white photographs and negatives documenting Doris Duke's trip to the Middle East. Negatives, 1938 (4 of 13) (Box 9, Folder PHDD066)
  - Black and white photographs and negatives documenting Doris Duke's trip to the Middle East. Unknown locations, 1938 (5 of 13) (Box 9, Folder PHDD066)
  - Black and white photographs and negatives documenting Doris Duke's trip to the Middle East. Unknown locations, 1938 (6 of 13) (Box 9, Folder PHDD066)
  - Black and white photographs and negatives documenting Doris Duke's trip to the Middle East. Aleppo, Baghdad, Camel Races, Damascus, 1938 (7 of 13) (Box 9, Folder PHDD066)
  - Black and white photographs and negatives documenting Doris Duke's trip to the Middle East. Chihil Sutun, 1938 (8 of 13) (Box 9, Folder PHDD066)
  - Black and white photographs and negatives documenting Doris Duke's trip to the Middle East. Egypt, Isfahan (Iran), Istanbul, Lebanon, 1938 (9 of 13) (Box 9, Folder PHDD066)
  - Black and white photographs and negatives documenting Doris Duke's trip to the Middle East. Luxor (Egypt), Palmyra, Persepolis, Turkey, 1938 (10 of 13) (Box 9, Folder PHDD066)
  - Black and white photographs and negatives documenting Doris Duke's trip to the Middle East. Various unidentified locations, 1938 (11 of 13) (Box 10, Folder PHDD066)
  - Black and white photographs and negatives documenting Doris Duke's trip to the Middle East. Various unidentified locations, 1938 (12 of 13) (Box 10, Folder PHDD066)
  - Black and white photographs and negatives documenting Doris Duke's trip to the Middle East. Various unidentified locations, 1938 (13 of 13) (Box 10, Folder PHDD066)
  - Selection of Black and white photographs documenting trips, sailing, and touring of Doris Duke and Alec Cunningham-Reid. Includes shots of couple on "Pious Puffin," Reid's boat, and of one of Reid's two sons, circa 1940 (Box 11, Folder PHDD078)
  - Selection of Black and white photographs of European travels of Alec Cunningham-Reid and Doris Duke, circa 1940 (Box 11, Folder PHDD079)
  - Selection of Black and white photographs documenting Doris Duke's tour around Italy. Unidentified man in one of the photos, circa 1945 (Box 11, Folder PHDD080)
  - Black and white photograph of Doris Duke with unidentified gentleman, 1941 (Box 11, Folder PHDD081)
  - Polaroids of Doris Duke, possibly at Rough Point. In photos, Doris Duke is wearing single strand of jade beads, 1969-1972 (Box 11, Folder PHDD082)
  - Selection of color photos documenting a vacation taken by Doris Duke and friends. Destination appears to be Bimini, an island of the Bahamas, 1978 (Box 11, Folder PHDD083)
  - Photos of Doris Duke's Boeing 737, circa 1990 (Box 11, Folder PHDD084)
  - Selection of Black and white photographs of Doris Duke, with friends including Marian Pascal. Location unknown though appears to be European, 1930-1935 (Box 11, Folder PHDD085)
  - Selection of Black and white photographs of Doris Duke with friends. Location unknown though it appears to be European. One of woman may possibly be Nanaline Duke, 1930-1935 (Box 11, Folder PHDD086)
  - Selection of color photographs of two of Doris Duke's dogs, circa 1945 (Box 11, Folder PHDD087)
  - Color photos of Doris Duke with military personnel, circa 1950 (Box 11, Folder PHDD088)
  - Selection of Black and white photographs of various events celebrating the 100th Anniversary of Founder's Day at Duke University, 1956 (Box 11, Folder PHDD089)
  - Group portrait of Duke University Board of Trustees and other members of faculty at Founders' Day, 1956 (Box 11, Folder PHDD090)
  - Selection of Black and white photographs of Doris Duke with two female companions, 1930-1935 (Box 11, Folder PHDD091)
  - Color photo of Doris Duke standing with an unidentified woman, 1970-1975 (Box 11, Folder PHDD092)
  - Color photo of Doris Duke, profile shot. Location is unknown. Photo is adhered to the bottom of a square piece of glass, undated (Box 11, Folder PHDD094)
  - Color photos of two of Doris Duke's dogs. The German Shepherd was named Sable, circa 1974 (Box 11, Folder PHDD095)
  - Black and white photograph of one of Doris Duke's dogs lying on the front lawn of the main residence, circa 1940s (Box 11, Folder PHDD096)
  - Black and white photographs of one of Doris Duke's dogs walking on snow at Duke Farms, undated (Box 11, Folder PHDD097)